<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io</id>
    <title>0K&apos;s Blog</title>
    <updated>2021-03-28T12:32:00.606Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>-273.15</subtitle>
    <logo>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/images/avatar.png</logo>
    <icon>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2021, 0K&apos;s Blog</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[《边界》]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/《边界》/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/《边界》/">
        </link>
        <updated>2021-01-06T14:12:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="边界">边界</h2>
<p>  我喜欢上“边界”这个词，源于美国反乌托邦小说《授者》。我也开始警觉自省，环视四周，果然，稀松的空气中有一条“边界”。我能感受到它。</p>
<p>  小说描绘了两条“边界”：一条有形，圈限人的行为与思考的边界；一条无形，设定人的职业、角色甚至情感的边界。由此，乌托邦建立，人们以各自适当的角色在适当的区域活动，直到主角乔纳斯冲破边界，释放人性中的一切善恶。同时，乔纳斯也冲破了另一层边界，以自由之姿向设置者进行反击。</p>
<p>  边界，英文“boundary”，词根为“bound”，即为捆绑、束缚、缠绕，犹如绷带缠绕木乃伊一样。绷带之于木乃伊，就是永恒的禁锢，使其在绷带所限区域内腐朽。想至此，不禁森然：边界于我看来即为一种圈限、束缚、牢狱，而画地为牢者可以是自己或是他人，也可以是社会价值观或是盲目的文凭主义之类。</p>
<p>  置身于边界中，我感到自己被占领了，被“他们”占领了。“他们”是操控程序的人，“他们”不一定是人，但确有其人。不仅我是如此，环视周围一张张脸，斑斑怯懦，点点怨愁，都是如此。因为在边界之中，因为设定好的角色，我们开始过分关注自我，关注自身存在状态的优劣，也因此对外界、对边界外广阔的世界失去了兴趣，由此丧失了冲动的激情和探求的动力，也丢失了冲破边界的勇气与羽翼。借萨特之言：我们沉浸其中，既感到不能忍受，却又与之相处愉快。确乎，忍受边界与拒绝忍受都是忍受，这种被圈困的感觉犹如吃了苍蝇一样，不将自己杀死是无法把它取出来的。我能感受到在边界、角色的荫翳下，自己失去了感动的爆发力，失去了对黎明、对新生的热爱，活在一种不闻、不动、无边的不正义中，任凭边界如绷带般慢慢收缩，榨干生命最后一滴血浆。</p>
<p>  正是由于对这种无形边界的不满，生命尝试着冲撞。在鲍鹏山的观点中，庄周几乎成功地冲破了对自己生命的定义，即冲破了边界。当他以“往矣！吾将曳尾于涂中”来拒绝尘嚣时，他跳开了一种边界的圈限，聪慧地远离了“火坑”。于是他像一棵独立守望心灵之月的树，由生站到了死。他似乎在跟世界比谁更无赖，谁更赤条条来去无牵挂，谁更无逻辑、无心肝。</p>
<p>  然而，这种冲撞的背后却听得见血泪的滴答声。庄子“眼冷心肠热”，对世界到底热肠挂肚，他对边界的冲撞成就了他曲高和寡的寥落才情。不仅庄周有如此尝试，艾丽丝·门罗亦在努力，在她的作品中，到处是罗素所言的“静静的绝望的真相”——不断地冲撞外力对自己的设定，却又不断地被挣扎的过去、无望的未来所捕获。在边界中，冲撞越猛，越被束缚，越易肝脑涂地，令人悚栗。</p>
<p>  所以冲破边界无望？</p>
<p>  在这永恒的生命困境中，我开始思考另外的途径。</p>
<p>  《死亡诗社》中的基丁老师站上讲桌，给了我一个方向。既然生命注定要被边界束缚，唯有扩大边界，站在边界之上，瞭望世界，才能免于那种不自觉的“木乃伊”状态。</p>
<p>  尼采曾有一句感伤之言：“宁愿绝望，胜于投降。”窃以为，不妨温柔些：“不如眺望，胜于投降，优于绝望。”以基丁为例，一个名校的老师，在所设的边界、角色内，保有清醒的双目，带领学生站在讲桌上，眺望万千世界中无尽的诗意与思趣，发出惠特曼所言的“野性的狂叫”。跃上讲桌的那一刻，学生在边界上打了个漂亮的“擦边球”，在眺望中看到了扩展的可能。</p>
<p>  这种想法与朱良志先生的“乾坤草亭”何其相似。他在对“亭子”这一物象的剖析中，发现了一种精妙的智慧。亭子，实为一种边界，然而和捆绑木乃伊的“绷带之界”不同，亭子四周无墙壁，能观亭外之物。坐于亭子中，既可遮挡一些风雨，又可眺望如烟景色，仰观宇宙之大，俯察品类之盛，在自由呼吸间精骛八极。此乐何极！由此观之，人该是在一种边界的范围内均匀呼吸，以扩展着的感觉和理性拓宽边界，由原点向外发散，思之无极。此可谓“不离亭子，不在亭子”的内在深意。这样的道理与远行之意不谋而合：所谓远行，该是带着对原点的怀念而上路的。正如边界是一个人在物质世界的立身之本一样， 唯有确立了一个生命的坐标，方有基础去探求。</p>
<p>  纵观“边界”之义，在我看来，人生所需的边界不该为绷带般的boundary，而该为四面通达的亭子。但无论置身于何地，扮演什么样的角色，都该怀有一份“狂躁”之感，一如前文的庄子、门罗，始终保有探求的冲动，始终在跃跃欲试的期待里不停地思考、冲撞。若非如此，无论在什么样的边界之中，你都会像一具被角色占领的木乃伊一般，任凭收缩的边界缩窄你的眼光，榨干你的脑浆。</p>
<p>  写到这里，我眼前浮现一幅画面：乾坤中芥籽般小亭，亭中一人神采飞扬。</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[积累]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/积累/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/积累/">
        </link>
        <updated>2020-09-06T08:38:51.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="日本俳句">日本俳句</h2>
<hr>
<p>我知道这世界，<br>
本如露水般短暂。<br>
然而，<br>
然而。<br>
——小林一茶<br>
<br><br>
天也醉樱花，<br>
云脚乱蹒跚。<br>
——野野口立圃<br>
<br><br>
日光穿透睡蝴蝶。<br>
——高桑阑更<br>
<br><br>
盛夏阳光里，<br>
听见蝴蝶相触声。<br>
——松濑青青<br>
<br><br>
故乡啊，<br>
挨着碰着，<br>
都是带刺的花。<br>
——小林一茶<br>
<br><br>
说是悲哀也可以说吧，<br>
事物的味道，<br>
我尝得太早了。<br>
——石川啄木<br>
<br><br>
山谷明月光，<br>
流萤皆彷徨。<br>
——原石鼎<br>
<br><br></p>
<h2 id="法国文学">法国文学</h2>
<hr>
<p>我现在渴望的并非快乐，但求自己不要无知。<br>
《加缪手记》  阿尔贝·加缪<br>
<br><br>
越被禁止，越引好奇，就像那深渊一样。脚迈不到的地方，目光可以到达；视线看不到的地方，思想仍能继续。人不管多么软弱，多么无能，但没有人不愿一试。<br>
《海上劳工》维克多·雨果<br>
<br><br>
一切自然美的深处都藏着某些不合人情的东西，连绵山丘、柔媚天色、婆娑树影，霎时间便失去了我们所赋予的幻想意义，从此比失去的天堂更遥远了。<br>
《西西弗神话》阿贝尔·加缪</p>
<p><br><br></p>
<h2 id="朴鲤的诗">朴鲤的诗</h2>
<hr>
<p>风经过，  <br>
轻易乱了白云的阵脚。  <br>
<br></p>
<p>山体被挖开巨口，<br>
而隧道终日沉默，<br>
等待——<br>
等待列车偶然的穿行。<br>
<br></p>
<p>纸张从虚空到圆满，<br>
亲历笔墨的死亡，<br>
最后，<br>
守着只言片语变皱变沧桑。<br>
<br></p>
<p>孤独矗立，<br>
存在就是为了粉碎障碍，<br>
拐杖和伞惺惺相惜。<br>
<br><br><br></p>
<p>蒸发——<br>
所有向上的事物皆轻盈欢畅，<br>
比如海洋湿气与林间浓雾，<br>
比如相爱时缥缈的心情。</p>
<p>欢聚——<br>
有关云朵的诸多元素:<br>
水滴、冰晶、微尘终于碰头，<br>
在虚浮的狂喜中构筑空中花园。</p>
<p>下坠——<br>
透支这座悬苑的筋骨，<br>
在低气压中开启雨的使命，<br>
以澄澈吞并污秽，以清冽安抚痛感。</p>
<p>云烟成雨，<br>
明日终将放晴。<br>
<br><br><br></p>
<p>爬山，从低谷跋涉至新的低谷。<br>
越冬，逃离十二月的霜雪，<br>
扎进二月的寒。<br>
所有曲折画成一个零。</p>
<p>而总有某些咬牙忍过的时刻不被虚度——<br>
山巅的稀薄空气值得胜者私藏;<br>
冬日偶然的回暖撩拨纷纷欲望。</p>
<p>端点，生命轨迹的启程与终结。<br>
伏线，时间精心预留的出口或者死路。<br>
事物总是两面——</p>
<p>英雄的灵魂与懦夫的胆子并不矛盾;<br>
少年郎心里也横尸遍野。<br>
<br><br><br></p>
<p>耗尽丁烷，耗尽烟草与浓雾，<br>
在虚设的火光中，<br>
亲眼目睹——<br>
猩红把黑暗灼穿几个窟窿;<br>
灰烬集体死亡，堆成坟头一角;</p>
<p>考验鼻腔，考验呼吸道与运气，<br>
此生如冻土般贫瘠，<br>
唯独不乏——<br>
延时的困倦与迟到的清醒，<br>
现代人的自由灵魂总擅长昼伏夜出。</p>
<p>如果可以，<br>
在这些被人为拉长的困倦长夜里，<br>
掐灭火光与失望，<br>
我想看到星光。<br>
<br></p>
<h2 id="初中书单">初中书单</h2>
<hr>
<p>《繁花不惊，银碗盛雪》 雪小禅<br>
《你好，旧时光》 八月长安<br>
《情书》 岩井俊二</p>
<p>《追风筝的人》<br>
《灿烂千阳》<br>
《群山回唱》卡勒德·胡赛尼三部曲</p>
<p>《活着》 余华<br>
《小王子》 安托万·德·圣·埃克苏佩里<br>
《病隙碎笔》 史铁生</p>
<p>《明朝那些事儿》 当年明月<br>
《三体》 刘慈欣<br>
《动物庄园》 乔治·奥威尔</p>
<p>《看见》柴静<br>
《目送》 龙应台<br>
《浮生六记》 沈复</p>
<h2 id="高中书单">高中书单</h2>
<hr>
<h3 id="素材利器类">素材利器类</h3>
<p>作文合唱团《看电影》<br>
《名师点评：为生命松绑》<br>
《精神明亮的人》 王开岭<br>
《我读》 梁文道<br>
《自由在高处》 熊培云</p>
<h3 id="美学史哲启蒙类">美学，史哲启蒙类</h3>
<p>《谈美》 朱光潜<br>
《西西弗神话》 加缪<br>
《中国哲学简史》 冯友兰<br>
《万历十五年》 黄仁宇</p>
<h3 id="心情治愈类">心情治愈类</h3>
<p>《瓦尔登湖》 梭罗<br>
《云雀叫了一整天》 木心诗歌<br>
《雪国》 川端康成</p>
<h3 id="反乌托邦三部曲">反乌托邦三部曲</h3>
<p>《1984》 乔治·奥威尔<br>
《我们》 扎米亚金<br>
《美丽新世界》 赫胥黎</p>
<h3 id="平凡疾苦的故事">平凡疾苦的故事</h3>
<p>《推拿》 毕飞宇<br>
《一个人的村庄》 刘亮程<br>
《平凡的世界》 路遥</p>
<h3 id="抓人眼球的小说">抓人眼球的小说</h3>
<p>《罗生门》 芥川龙之介<br>
《1Q84》 村上春树<br>
《变形记》 卡夫卡</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/hello-world/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/hello-world/">
        </link>
        <updated>2020-08-13T01:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to <a href="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</a>! This is your very first post. Check <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/">documentation</a> for more info. If you get any problems when using Hexo, you can find the answer in <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/troubleshooting.html">troubleshooting</a> or you can ask me on <a href="https://github.com/hexojs/hexo/issues">GitHub</a>.</p>
<h2 id="quick-start">Quick Start</h2>
<h3 id="create-a-new-post">Create a new post</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">$ hexo new &quot;My New Post&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>More info: <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/writing.html">Writing</a></p>
<h3 id="run-server">Run server</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">$ hexo server
</code></pre>
<p>More info: <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/server.html">Server</a></p>
<h3 id="generate-static-files">Generate static files</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">$ hexo generate
</code></pre>
<p>More info: <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/generating.html">Generating</a></p>
<h3 id="deploy-to-remote-sites">Deploy to remote sites</h3>
<pre><code class="language-bash">$ hexo deploy
</code></pre>
<p>More info: <a href="https://hexo.io/docs/one-command-deployment.html">Deployment</a></p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Game]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/The-Great-Game/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/The-Great-Game/">
        </link>
        <updated>2020-03-31T16:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sorry for the delay in posting. I needed a few days to get my head around what just happened.</p>
<p>It began, as everything did, with a big bang. There was apparently a gas leak in the house across the street. Of course, my time living with Sherlock means I know how meaningless the word 'apparently' can be. The police investigated and discovered that the house had been wired with explosives. The only other thing they found inside the house was a box. And inside the box was an envelope. And inside the envelope was, of all things, a bright pink phone. Regular readers of my blog might remember the case I called '<a href="http://www.johnwatsonblog.co.uk/blog/07february" title="A Study In Pink">A Study In Pink</a>' . Needless to say, it was a bit of a surprise.</p>
<p>As is my sudden use of phrases like &quot;regular readers of my blog&quot;. It seems I'm starting to enjoy writing up my life. It helps, though, when I discover that half of Scotland Yard are reading it. More on that later!</p>
<p>So, we switched on the phone and there was a message.</p>
<p>Beep. Beep. Beep. Beep. Beep.</p>
<p>Five beeps or pips. Sherlock knew immediately that it was a warning. There were these secret societies who used to send five orange pips to people as a threat. There was also a picture of an empty flat which Sherlock recognised. It was downstairs. 221C Baker Street! We rushed over there and discovered a pair of trainers.</p>
<p>And then the pink phone rang. It was a woman. She was crying. It turns out that whoever was organising all this had arranged for this woman to be kidnapped and wrapped in explosives. If she didn't say exactly what she was told to say... Sherlock, naturally, was immediately caught up in the adventure. Didn't even register that some innocent person somewhere was going through Hell. The crying woman told us we had twelve hours to solve the first problem.</p>
<p>We went to Barts so that Sherlock could examine the trainers. I, as usual, didn't have a clue what the question was never mind the answer. We met up with Molly Hooper who introduced us to her boyfriend, Jim. Apparently, he worked in IT. There's that word 'apparently' again. Oh, and I've just seen <a href="http://www.mollyhooper.co.uk/blog/25march" title="how they first met">how they first met</a> .</p>
<p>Anyway, Jim left and Sherlock revealed to Molly that the bloke was clearly gay. As usual, he didn't care that this might, you know, not exactly be what she wanted to hear!</p>
<p>So, back to the trainers. Sherlock naturally got me to humiliate myself by examining them myself and getting everything wrong. He told me that they were twenty years old and that the pollen on them revealed they were from Sussex. Then he remembered a name - Carl Powers, a boy who had died when Sherlock was a kid. Everyone had assumed it was a tragic swimming accident but Sherlock was always confused by the boy's missing trainers. Now they'd turned up twenty years later and addressed to him. Sherlock discovered traces of Clostridium botulinim on Carl's trainers and concluded that he'd been murdered - the poison having been introduced to Carl's eczema medicine. Sherlock needed to let the killer know he'd worked it out so he typed a message on his website. I know some of you were confused by his <a href="http://www.thescienceofdeduction.co.uk/forum/page4" title="bizarre posts the other day">bizarre posts the other day</a> .</p>
<p>The crying woman then phoned again and was allowed to tell us where she was. The police found her and she was ok. Sherlock pissed me off though. He described the whole set-up as elegant. I asked him what he meant and he said that &quot;I can't be the only person to get bored&quot;. Clearly, the killer was targeting him directly and he loved it.</p>
<p>Beep. Beep. Beep. Beep.</p>
<p>Another message. Another photo. This time it was of an abandoned sports car. The phone rang. It was a man, as terrified as the woman had been earlier. He told us we had eight hours. â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“ from Scotland Yard located the car and Sherlock examined it. It had been hired from a company called Janus Cars by a man called â–“â–“â–“ â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“ - a man who had disappeared. This one was pretty straightforward for Sherlock. Just one chat with the missing man's wife and a visit to Janus Cars and he had it all wrapped up. It was a simple insurance scam. Again, he posted the answer on his blog. The man wrapped in explosives was found and released. Turns out he'd been in central London. God, if Sherlock had got it wrong... The other thing is, like I say, he was enjoying it. Him and this mysterious killer were playing a game. Me, Mrs H, the people with the bombs, everyone else, we were just pawns. I thought back to a name we'd heard a couple of times - Moriarty. Could this be him? When I mentioned this, Sherlock's eyes lit up.</p>
<p>Beep. Beep. Beep.</p>
<p>Another message. A third photo. This time it was someone I recognised but Sherlock didn't have a clue who she was. It's nice to occasionally be the clever one. The picture was of the recently deceased <a href="http://www.connieprince.co.uk/" title="Connie Prince">Connie Prince</a> . Apparently, she'd died as a result of a tetanus infection but clearly our killer was suggesting otherwise. Again, we received a phone call. This time it was an old woman - and she was blind. I mean, who would do that? How could anyone do that? I went along to visit Connie's brother, Kenny. Sherlock went onto some internet forums and, with his usual tact and diplomacy, <a href="%5B%E9%93%BE%E6%8E%A5%E5%9C%B0%E5%9D%80%5D(http://www.connieprince.co.uk/message-board)" title="got answers that way">got answers that way</a> . Between us, we worked out that while Connie's death had been made to look like the result of a tetanus infection, it had actually been caused by poison - their houseboy, â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“, had overdosed her on Botox! It would have almost been funny were it not for what happened next. Sherlock posted a message to his blog and, like before, the old woman called us. But this one made a mistake. She started to tell us about the man who'd tied her up and... He blew her up.</p>
<p>She lived in a block of flats. In Glasgow. Twelve people died.</p>
<p>I still can't quite get my head around it. This game between Sherlock and his... nemesis? Is that the right word? Twelve totally random innocent people had died because of it. I got so angry with Sherlock that morning. He didn't care. He admitted it. He just didn't care. As he pointed out, caring wouldn't save lives. I asked him if he found it easy not to care and he said yes. It was that simple. Maybe Sally Donovan is right. Maybe he is a freak.</p>
<p>Beep. Beep.</p>
<p>Another photo. This time of the Thames. Sherlock called Scotland Yard and they told him about a body that had been pulled out of the river. We went along and within minutes, Sherlock had worked out he was a security guard and that he was probably linked to a lost painting that had recently been rediscovered and put on display at the Hickman Gallery. Oh, and he revealed that the painting was a fake. I could explain how he did it but I think it's one of those 'you had to be there' moments. He also worked out what had killed the security guard. I say 'what' although technically it was 'who'. But, having seen the man, 'what' is probably a better definition. He was an assassin known as the Golem. He killed people by squeezing the air out of their body with his bare hands! Why he would have done this to some poor security guard was still a mystery so I went to the guy's flat and discovered a voicemail message from a Professor â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“. She had called him in response to him having discovered that something somewhere was wrong. The only other clue was that he was into astronomy. Sherlock worked out that the Golem had killed the security guard because he'd worked out that the painting was a fake. We concluded that Professor â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“ worked at a planetarium and rushed over there. But we were too late. The Golem was there and it killed her. Then, it attacked Sherlock. I don't think I've actually seen him scared before. Me, I was bricking it! I'd seen horror in Afghanistan. But this man was barely human. He really was a monster! I managed to rescue Sherlock (by whacking the Golem with my gun - I never said I was subtle) but the creature got away.</p>
<p>We returned to the gallery and Sherlock confronted the curator. She denied everything - insisting that the painting was real - and there didn't seem to be much we could do. Then the phone rang once more.</p>
<p>It was a child.</p>
<p>The child started to count down from ten. Sherlock was screaming into the phone that the painting was a fake but the killer clearly wanted proof. Sherlock stared at the painting as the child continued to count down to his own death. And then Sherlock, at the last minute, worked it out. It was how the security guard had guessed it was a fake and why he'd phoned a professor at a planetarium. There was a supernova in the painting that didn't appear in our skies until 1858. Therefore, the painting couldn't have been painted by an artist living in the 1640s. The child stopped counting.</p>
<p>The curator admitted that she'd arranged for the painting to be created. She'd been put in touch with various people and they'd all seemed to be working for one man. You've guessed it. Moriarty.</p>
<p>Back at the flat, and we waited for another call. Nothing seemed to be happening though so I decided to visit my girlfriend, Sarah. I had just left the flat when a taxi pulled up alongside me. The taxi driver asked if I wanted a lift but I told him I was getting the Tube. He then said that he hadn't been asking me, he'd been telling me. I looked at him and I saw the gun pointing at me and so I got into the taxi.</p>
<p>They must have knocked me out because the next thing I can remember is waking up to the smell of chlorine. I was in a sports centre, near the swimming pool. And I was wearing a bomb. I could feel it under the jacket they'd put me in. Then a voice sounded in my ear and I realised I was wearing some kind of earpiece. It said that I knew the drill and I was to repeat word-for-word what he said otherwise I'd never be writing my blog again.</p>
<p>I was made to walk out into the swimming pool area where, I discovered, Sherlock was waiting. The voice in my ear, which I vaguely recognised, told me to say some stuff - which, I realised, gave the impression that I was behind it all. That I, John Watson, was Moriarty. I could see the look in Sherlock's eyes - a flash of, not anger, but hurt. For a second, he looked like a little, lost child. I should have been horrified that he'd even doubt me for a second but, to be honest, it was so refreshingly human of him. He actually did value our friendship. He did, despite himself, care. Then he saw the explosives on me and he realised what was happening.</p>
<p>And at that moment, out stepped Moriarty. It was Jim. Molly Hooper's boyfriend from the IT department at Barts! Even that little meeting had been part of the game. The two men talked, both clearly pleased to, at last, be face to face. Again, I felt like a pawn in their game. Especially when a laser sight appeared on my chest. One wrong move and some stranger in the dark would shoot the explosives. I watched as they talked. Jim Moriarty was the total opposite to Sherlock but they were also so very alike. He was a consulting criminal. People came to him and he arranged whatever they wanted. And while they talked, I stood there wearing enough explosives to kill all of us. I was the only one who seemed even aware of this. Suddenly, I grabbed Moriarty. I knew that his assistant (his John Watson?) wouldn't kill him. But the laser sight simply moved to Sherlock's head and I was forced to let go. For a second, I wondered if Sherlock would have done the same for me but then all I knew for certain was, at that moment, I knew I was going to die.</p>
<p>Except I didn't because Moriarty changed his mind. He said that he'd kill Sherlock one day but that, for now, he was letting us go. It really was just a game to him. He left and Sherlock ripped the explosives off of me. We were getting our breath back when suddenly so many laser sights appeared. Moriarty returned and said he had changed his mind again!! We were going to die, after all. Sherlock simply pointed his gun at the discarded explosives. If we were going to die, so was Moriarty.</p>
<p>I held my breath for what seemed like months. I had no idea what either of them would do. Moriarty clearly had no discernible human feelings and Sherlock had claimed not to care. Could this be it? Was I really going to die? In a sports centre?</p>
<p>Which is when Moriarty's phone rang. He took the call and called off his gunman. He was letting us live. And, as I finally breathed out, he left.</p>
<p>And that's how Sherlock Holmes and I lived to see another day.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Blind Banker]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/The-Blind-Banker/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/The-Blind-Banker/">
        </link>
        <updated>2010-03-27T16:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It all began with Sherlock and I visiting the bank. We'd been called in by an old school friend of his. The man was a banker and pretty much what you'd expect. Someone had broken into their offices and sprayed graffiti across a painting. Nothing too interesting about that, you might think. Except that whoever did it, they didn't show up on any CCTV. The bank's offices were like Fort Knox but there was nothing. No sign of who'd done it.</p>
<p>Sherlock worked out that we needed to speak to one of the bankers, â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“ â–“â–“â–“ â–“â–“â–“â–“. So we went to his flat but he was already dead. It looked like suicide but of course it wasn't. The graffiti at the bank had been a warning. A death threat. The police still thought it was suicide and I have to admit... well, it was a locked room. A dead man. Gun in his hand. It did look like suicide.</p>
<p>But Sherlock, of course, had noticed from every little thing in the flat that â–“â–“â–“ â–“â–“â–“â–“ was left-handed and that the gun was in his right hand. He said he was 'amazed' that we hadn't noticed. Sad thing is, he genuinely was. That sort of thing comes so easy for him.</p>
<p>Then, almost as if to confirm that what Sherlock was saying was true, there was another murder. A journalist. He was also in a locked room. He'd also presumably thought he was safe from whoever it was that killed him. We needed to find out whatever it was that connected the two men. Sherlock worked out that the graffiti was like an ancient secret code. So we went to meet a 'friend' of his. I think the correct term is 'delinquent'. I called him much worse.</p>
<p>To cut a long story short, I found myself at the police station, reading â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“ â–“â–“â–“â–“â–“'s diary. And that led me and Sherlock to a Chinese emporium on Shaftesbury Ave. It was a shop full of tat basically but we got what we wanted...the graffiti tags were numbers. Old Chinese numbers. Sherlock then noticed that nobody had been in the flat above the shop for a few days... but that the window was open. So, of course, he had to break in and leave me standing outside while he explored. It turned out the flat belonged to a woman who worked in a museum. By now, I have to admit, I was pretty confused. All these people and places that seemed to be linked randomly. Our visit to the bank seemed like a lifetime away.</p>
<p>The woman at the museum, Soo Lin, was really quite brilliant. She was hiding in the museum, fearing for her life. She was hiding there, though, so she could continue looking after some old Chinese teapots. It was both absurd but also strangely beautiful. I think even Sherlock was impressed by her. She told us about a huge smuggling operation and of an assassin sent to kill those who betrayed the organisation. Which is what had happened to the banker and the journalist.</p>
<p>And which is then what happened to her.</p>
<p>So we worked out that the smuggling ring was trading in Chinese antiquities. Both the banker and the journalist were able to bring them to the UK because they travelled a lot and the gang had contacted the woman because she was an expert in such things. We found out where they were selling what they'd stolen but we still needed to work out what the code meant. We realised that the numbers were references to books. Each bit of the code indicated a certain page in a certain book. The problem was working out which book. It needed to be something that anyone would have.</p>
<p>And, meanwhile, I went on a date. I'd met someone. She's called Sarah and she's great. Sherlock gave me tickets for the circus so I could take her. Only, of course, he invited himself along as well. Mine and Sarah's first date and I've got the madman detective there. I kind of figured that it wasn't going to go well. And sure enough, one minute Sherlock was standing next to us, the next he was on the stage fighting with a mad warlord assassin. Luckily, Sarah didn't seem to mind helping me to help him. We saved his life and then returned to the flat. And Sherlock was, of course, his usual rude and arrogant self, ignoring Sarah. Until she pointed out that Soo Lin had already translated part of the code. Sherlock rushed out to do God knows what, leaving me and Sarah to be kidnapped. The date really hadn't gone well.</p>
<p>We found ourselves being held at gunpoint by an opera singer and her assassins. My main concern was Sarah, of course. She hadn't agreed to this. She hadn't agreed to any of this. And, of course, the biggest irony was that they didn't even want me. They'd mistaken me for Sherlock. They were going to kill Sarah because they thought I was Sherlock Holmes!</p>
<p>Sherlock found us and we managed to escape and shut down the operation. It turned out that they'd been looking for a hairpin. All this madness and death was because of a hairpin! An Empress's hairpin apparently but still, a hairpin. Sherlock even knew where it was...he'd seen it before. And that was it. Case closed. Over a couple days we'd encountered Chinese assassins, killer opera singers, secret codes, secret messages in the A-Z, smugglers and god knows what else. I'd even met a beautiful lady. It was all very James Bond.</p>
<p>I can't deny that I prefer this kind of life. Being a civilian doesn't suit me. But the thing is, this life we've chosen isn't safe. Sherlock chooses to be this crusading consulting detective and I choose to be his colleague. But he's becoming known. People know of him. It's like that taxi driver said about how this Moriarty knew about him. Then the opera singer, she knew all about him. How long before someone else comes after him? And what happens to the people like Sarah or Mrs Hudson when that happens?</p>
<p>All these people he involves in his adventures... They're not safe. We're not safe. There are forces out there and they're coming for Sherlock Holmes.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[FYI]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/FYI/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/FYI/">
        </link>
        <updated>2010-03-26T16:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, it's been an interesting few days. I've got myself a job. And I also helped break up an international smuggling ring. More details to follow.</p>
<p>Oh, but before I write it up. Important information!!</p>
<p>This is me</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="1"><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/11/06/8Bkp1rMhIRYwJgi.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>This is Sherlock</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="2"><img src="https://i.loli.net/2020/11/06/n4NcJRldSCgvbfz.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Okay? Criminals of London, please note which is which! It'll save us all a lot of time and hassle. I've changed my profile picture back to avoid any further confusion.</p>
<p>In other news, Sherlock's had another of those coded messages, if you fancied proving yourself. Go to <a href="http://www.thescienceofdeduction.co.uk/" title="The Science of Deduction">The Science of Deduction</a> .</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[A rant]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/A-rant/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/A-rant/">
        </link>
        <updated>2010-03-22T16:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you know what I hate? Those unmanned checkout machines. They're there to 'save time' but they don't. They clearly don't. Nobody can use them. Staff have to come over and help. How do they save time?</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diamonds are forever]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/Diamonds-are-forever/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/Diamonds-are-forever/">
        </link>
        <updated>2010-03-22T16:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Except they're not. No story here because Sherlock decided not to take the case. Apparently a missing diamond isn't 'interesting' enough.</p>
<p>Still, we discovered a body today so that's something for him to get excited about.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Study in Pink]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/A-Study-in-Pink/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/A-Study-in-Pink/">
        </link>
        <updated>2010-02-06T16:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've blacked out a few names and places because of legal matters but, other than that, this is what happened on the night I moved in with Sherlock Holmes.</p>
<p>When I first met Sherlock, he told me my life story. He could tell so much about me from my limp, my tan and my mobile phone. And that's the thing with him. It's no use trying to hide what you are because Sherlock sees right through everyone and everything in seconds. What's incredible, though, is how spectacularly ignorant he is about some things.</p>
<p>This morning, for example, he asked me who the Prime Minister was. Last week he seemed to genuinely not know the Earth goes round the Sun. Seriously. He didn't know. He didn't think the Sun went round the Earth or anything. He just didn't care. I still can't quite believe it. In so many ways, he's the cleverest person I've ever met but there are these blank spots that are almost terrifying. At least I've got used to him now. Well, I say that, I suspect I'll never really get used to him. It's just, on that first night, I literally had no idea of what was to come. I mean, how could I?</p>
<p>I was looking at the flat, surprised at the state it was already in, when DI 鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔from Scotland Yard burst in. Sherlock, of course, already knew why he was there. There'd been another death - this time, in 鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻�. Sherlock asked me to join him and I went along, intrigued. In the taxi, he explained how he'd deduced everything about me the previous day - how he'd picked up on every word I said, every action, tiny little things about my phone. It was extraordinary. I'd try to explain it here but I don't think I'd be able to do him justice. Go to his site, <a href="http://www.thescienceofdeduction.co.uk/" title="The Science of Deduction">The Science of Deduction</a> and see for yourself how his mind works.</p>
<p>I was still surprised that, even being the genius he clearly is, the police would come to him for help. He said he was a 'consulting detective'. Naturally, being the arrogant so-and-so he is, he'd had to give himself his own unique job title.</p>
<p>We arrived in 鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻� where, to my surprise, he introduced me as his colleague. The police seemed surprised by this as well I get the impression he'd not had 'colleagues' before. It was a body of a woman, dressed in pink. And she'd been poisoned. Again, Sherlock just looked at her and he knew everything about her. The way she was dressed. Splatters of mud on her leg. What was there and, more importantly, what was missing. Her suitcase. And it was that which excited him. The missing pink suitcase.</p>
<p>He left the body and ran outside to searched for it, naturally leaving me behind. I spoke to a policewoman and she summed Sherlock up. She said 'he gets off on it.' And he does. He didn't care about the dead woman or any of the other victims. I suspect if he came back and found me and our landlady lying here with our throats cut, he'd just see it as an intellectual exercise. 'Fantastic' he'd exclaim, rubbing his hands together. 'But the door was locked so how did they kill each other?' The policewoman, she called him a psychopath. That seems harsh and it was hardly a professional diagnosis but I look back at what I wrote about him when I first met him. I called him the madman.</p>
<p>So I went back to Baker Street and Sherlock asked me to send a text message. He'd found her suitcase and discovered that the victim's phone was missing. He knew the killer would have it, so there I was, texting a serial killer.</p>
<p>He'd found the woman's missing suitcase because he'd known it would be pink, like the woman's clothes. It hadn't even crossed my mind and when I said this, he told me I was an idiot. He didn't mean to be offensive, he just said what he thought. I've been called worse things but his bluntness was still a bit of a surprise. He just didn't care about being polite or anything like that. I was starting to understand why he didn't seem to have many 'colleagues'.</p>
<p>After that, we went on a stakeout. We waited in a restaurant to see if the killer would visit the address I'd texted him. Across the road, we saw a taxi pull up. We ran out, but it drove off. Sherlock insisted on chasing it and luckily he seemed to have an intimate knowledge of London's backstreets. Of course, as I realised afterwards, he's probably memorised the London A-Z. We ran down street after street and we managed to catch up with the taxi - only to discover that the passenger wasn't our killer. He'd only just arrived in the UK. It was the most ridiculous night of my life - I mean, an actual chase through London. People don't do that, not really. But we did.</p>
<p>And, of course, by doing this, Sherlock proved my limp was psychosomatic. Did I mention he's clever?</p>
<p>We returned to the flat to discover that 鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔 and the police were there, examining the suitcase. It was actually pretty funny seeing how offended Sherlock was by this. I genuinely think he believes himself to be above the law. And he couldn't stand the fact that 鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔 had got one over him. 鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔鈻撯枔 described Sherlock as a child and, in many ways, that's what he is. I said that he doesn't care about what others think and that he's arrogant because of this but it's not really that. It's not that he doesn't care, it's that he genuinely doesn't understand that it's normal to care. It's normal to worry about what other people think. Like a child, he just doesn't understand the rules of society - which, of course, is probably why he's so good at working the rest of us out.</p>
<p>Sherlock thinks everyone else is stupid so he's like a kid at Christmas when it turns out that one of us have done something clever. I'm not talking about me but our murder victim. She hadn't lost her phone. She hadn't left it behind. She knew she was going to die so she'd left her phone in the taxi - And, like all modern phones, it had a GPS system so you could locate it. That brilliant woman had led us to her killer.</p>
<p>And he was outside. He was outside our flat - in his taxi! We'd chased him halfway across London, thinking he'd been driving the killer - but he was the killer himself. That was how he'd manage to get to his victims - just by picking them up in his cab. Of course, Sherlock being completely and utterly mad, got into the taxi so he could talk to him. Again, he wasn't interested in the 'rules'. He wasn't interested in how the driver had done all this. I don't think he was particularly interested in stopping him and it didn't even cross his mind to let the police know that the man they were looking for was outside. All Sherlock Holmes was interested in was discovering why the killer had done it. He wanted to be alone with the killer so he could question him. That was more important than anything else - despite the obvious threat to his own life.</p>
<p>The taxi driver drove him to a college of further education so they could both educate each other on - well, on how their minds worked, I guess. It's not something I'll ever really understand and, to be honest, I'm not sure I ever want to understand it. To be that much of a psychopath. To be that above the rest of us. To be that dangerous. It's pretty terrifying.</p>
<p>Afterwards, Sherlock told me what happened. The taxi driver had a brain aneurism. He was dying. He'd pick up his victims and take them somewhere. Then he'd give them a choice. Take one of two pills - one of which was harmless and one of which would kill them. Their only other choice was that he would shoot them. It makes me furious to think about those poor people who got into his taxi - one of them was just a kid! They must have gone through hell. But Sherlock, mad old Sherlock, he understood him. As far the taxi driver was concerned, he was outliving people. He was giving himself the power of life and death. And I do, I genuinely think Sherlock understood this.</p>
<p>Myself and the police had managed to work out where they'd gone so we'd driven after them. But it was too late. By the time we got there, I could see that Sherlock was going to take one of the pills. It wasn't because he had to but because it was a game of wits. He wasn't going to let this other arrogant, pompous psychopath win. Which is when someone shot the taxi driver. Someone like that's bound to have enemies so it shouldn't have been a surprise but I hadn't seen anyone shot since Afghanistan. It's something you never really get used to. That someone could have the power of life and death over someone else - but I'm glad whoever it was did it, because they undoubtedly saved Sherlock's life. And, frankly, after everything that man had done to those innocent people who got into his car, a quick death like that was better than he deserved.</p>
<p>And after all that? Well, me and my flatmate went for a Chinese. Like I say, he really does know some great restaurants.</p>
<p>There was one other thing though. Before the taxi driver died, he said a name. A name of someone or something that had helped him. Moriarty. I've never heard of it and neither has Sherlock. Of course, he loves it. He thinks he's found himself an arch-enemy. He's a strange child.</p>
<p>And since that night? It hasn't stopped. Oh, there's so much more I've got to tell you.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Secret code]]></title>
        <id>https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/Secret-code/</id>
        <link href="https://chaizhaoyuan0.github.io/Secret-code/">
        </link>
        <updated>2010-01-31T16:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sorry, I'm still typing up what happened last night but in the meantime, Sherlock's been sent some secret coded message or something. He's looking for people to help with it.</p>
<p>If you fancy giving it a go, then go to his site, <a href="http://www.thescienceofdeduction.co.uk/" title="The Science of Deduction">The Science of Deduction</a></p>
<p><strong>Update added 01 February:</strong> Could the Roman Emperor be Caesar?</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>